# Curriculum Vitæ Jean-Philippe Labbé

(January 4, 2021)

Arbeitsgruppe Diskrete Geometrie

Institut für Mathematik, Freie Universität Berlin Arnimallee 2, Berlin, 14195 Deutschland

labbe at math.fu-berlin.de http://page.mi.fu-berlin.de/labbe Phone: +49 30 838 75653

### AREA OF SPECIALIZATION

My research is at the intersection of combinatorics, discrete geometry and group theory. My speciality is combining geometric, combinatorial and computational approaches to study properties of algebraic and topological structures. In particular, my research merges abstract modelizations and computational experimentations to tackle open problems related to Coxeter groups, polytopes (in particular permutahedra, associahedra, and their applications to quantum physics), triangulations, and simplicial complexes.

### MSC2010 keywords:

05 Combinatorics: Groups and algebras, Reflection and Coxeter groups (05E15, 20F55, 20B40)

52 Discrete Geometry: Combinatorial and computational aspects of polytopes, Special polytopes (52B05, 52B12, 52B55)

### WORK EXPERIENCE

11/2020 -	Privatdozent Freie Universität Berlin, Germany
10/2016 - 09/2020	Research Fellow, SFB Transregio "Discretization in Geometry and Dynamics" Freie Universität Berlin, Germany
10/2014 - 09/2016	Research Fellow, Israel Science Foundation Grant of Prof. Eran Nevo Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Israel
02/2015 - 10/2015	Research Fellow, Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec) Universitad de Cantabria, Santander, Spain
07/2013 - 06/2014	Research Fellow, SFB Transregio "Discretization in Geometry and Dynamics" Freie Universität Berlin, Germany

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2017 -	University courses
	Bachelor courses: Wahrscheinlichkeit & Statistik, Seminar zur Geometrie
	Master courses: Discrete Mathematics I, Seminar Discrete Mathematics I
2016 -	Programming
	Sagemath: SageDays 79 (Teaching python and Sagemath), Friday Coding Sprints
2008 - 2010	Teaching Assistant
	Algèbre Matricielle, Combinatoire, Algèbre II
EDUCATION	

### EDUCATION

07/2020	Habilitation, Mathematics / Freie Universität Berlin Title: Convex Geometry of Subword Complexes of Coxeter Groups Habilitation Presentation: Jones Unknotting Conjecture
10/2010 - 07/2013	<b>Dr. rer. nat.</b> , Mathematics / Freie Universität Berlin Title: Polyhedral Combinatorics of Coxeter Groups Advisor: Prof. Günter M. Ziegler
05/2008 - 08/2010	Maîtrise ès Sciences, Mathématiques / Université du Québec à Montréal Title: Approche combinatoire des amas par les éléments triés des groupes de Coxeter Advisor: Prof. Christophe Hohlweg
09/2005 - 04/2008	Bachelier ès Sciences, Mathématiques / Université Laval, Québec City
09/2007 - 12/2007 09/2006 - 12/2006	Math in Moscow / Independent University of Moscow Budapest Semesters in Mathematics / Eötvös University

#### ARTICLES IN PREPARATION

- [1] Christian Schilling, Federico Castillo, and Jean-Philippe Labbé, Comprehensive foundation of onematrix functional theory for excited states, in preparation (2020) 20 pp.
- [2] Winfried Bruns, Vincent Delecroix, Matthias Köppe, and Jean-Philippe Labbé, Algebraic polyhedra in Sagemath with Normaliz, in preparation (2020) 21 pp.
- [3] Federico Castillo, Jean-Philippe Labbé, and Christian Schilling, *Paulitopes*, in preparation (2020) 15 pp.

#### Preprints

- [4] Michael Cuntz, Sophia Elia, and Jean-Philippe Labbé, Congruence normality of simplicial hyperplane arrangements via oriented matroids, arXiv:2009.14152 (2020) 39 pp.
- [5] Jean-Philippe Labbé, Combinatorial foundations for geometric realizations of subword complexes of Coxeter groups, arXiv: 2003.02753 (2020) 34 pp.

### BOOK CHAPTERS

[6] Ana Maria Botero, Jean-Philippe Labbé, and Lauren Williams. *Introduction to total positivity and cluster algebras*. In: *ECCO – Lectures Notes*. (Book in preparation). Cambridge University Press, 2019, 32 pp.

#### Publications

- [7] Joseph Doolittle, Jean-Philippe Labbé, Carsten Lange, Rainer Sinn, Jonathan Spreer, and Günter M. Ziegler, Combinatorial inscribability obstructions for higher-dimensional polytopes, Mathematika 66 (2020) no. 4, 927–953.
- [8] Jean-Philippe Labbé and Carsten Lange, Cambrian acyclic domains: counting c-singletons, Order 37 (2020) no. 3, 571–603.
- [9] Jean-Philippe Labbé, Günter Rote, and Günter M. Ziegler, Area difference bounds for dissections of a square into an odd number of triangles, Exp. Math. 29 (2020) no. 3, 253–275.
- [10] Sarah B. Brodsky, Cesar Ceballos, and Jean-Philippe Labbé, Cluster algebras of type  $D_4$ , tropical planes, and the positive tropical Grassmannian, Beitr. Algebra Geom. **58** (2017) no. 1, 25–46.
- [11] Hao Chen and Jean-Philippe Labbé, *Limit directions for Lorentzian Coxeter systems*, Groups Geom. Dyn. **11** (2017) no. 2, 469–498.
- [12] Jean-Philippe Labbé, Brocoli: Sagemath package dealing with LImit ROots of COxeter groups, https://github.com/jplab/brocoli (2017) version 1.0.0 3500 lines.
- [13] Jean-Philippe Labbé, Thibault Manneville, and Francisco Santos, *Hirsch polytopes with exponentially long combinatorial segments*, Math. Program. **165** (2017) no. 2, Ser. A, 663–688.
- [14] Jean-Philippe Labbé and Eran Nevo, Bounds for entries of  $\gamma$ -vectors of flag homology spheres, SIAM J. Discrete Math. **31** (2017) no. 3, 2064–2078.
- [15] Christophe Hohlweg and Jean-Philippe Labbé, On inversion sets and the weak order in Coxeter groups, European J. Combin. **55** (2016) 1–19.
- [16] Nantel Bergeron, Cesar Ceballos, and Jean-Philippe Labbé, Fan realizations of type A subword complexes and multi-associahedra of rank 3, Discrete Comput. Geom. 54 (2015) no. 1, 195–231.
- [17] Hao Chen and Jean-Philippe Labbé, Lorentzian Coxeter systems and Boyd-Maxwell ball packings, Geom. Dedicata 174 (2015) 43–73.
- [18] Cesar Ceballos, Jean-Philippe Labbé, and Christian Stump, Subword complexes, cluster complexes, and generalized multi-associahedra, J. Algebraic Combin. 39 (2014) no. 1, 17–51.
- [19] Christophe Hohlweg, Jean-Philippe Labbé, and Vivien Ripoll, Asymptotical behaviour of roots of infinite Coxeter groups, Canad. J. Math. 66 (2014) no. 2, 323–353.
- [20] Srečko Brlek, Jean-Philippe Labbé, and Michel Mendès France, Combinatorial variations on Cantor's diagonal, J. Combin. Theory Ser. A 119 (2012) no. 3, 655–667.

### Conference Proceedings

[21] Jean-Philippe Labbé. Universal Oriented Matroids for Subword Complexes of Coxeter Groups. In: FPSAC 2020. 2020, pp. 12.

- [22] Nantel Bergeron, Cesar Ceballos, and Jean-Philippe Labbé. Fan realizations of type A subword complexes and multi-associahedra of rank 3. In: Proceedings of FPSAC 2015. DMTCS Proc. Assoc. DMTCS, Nancy, 2015, 429–440.
- [23] Hao Chen and Jean-Philippe Labbé. Lorentzian Coxeter groups and Boyd-Maxwell ball packings. In: 26th FPSAC. DMTCS Proc. Assoc. DMTCS, Nancy, 2014, 103–111.
- [24] Cesar Ceballos, Jean-Philippe Labbé, and Christian Stump. *Multi-cluster complexes*. In: 24th FP-SAC. DMTCS Proc. Assoc. DMTCS, Nancy, 2012, 1–8.
- [25] Christophe Hohlweg, Jean-Philippe Labbé, and Vivien Ripoll. Asymptotical behaviour of roots of infinite Coxeter groups I. In: 24th FPSAC. DMTCS Proc. Assoc. DMTCS, Nancy, 2012, 851–862.

### HONORS, AWARDS AND GRANTS

2011 -	Ambassador, Centre d'étude Collégial, Lac-Mégantic (Québec)
2016	Deux frères dans les hautes sphères des mathématiques internationales News article, Ronald Martel, <i>La Tribune</i> , appeared 14 March 2016
01/2015 - 12/2016	Postdoctoral Research Fellowship – <b>by Competition</b> Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec), (70 000\$CAD)
10/2013	Phase II – Certificate of Distinction  Berlin Mathematical School
02/2013	Public Prize for Best Talk  Math Slam (Sandwich Theory) – Berlin Mathematical School Conference
09/2010 - 08/2013	Doctoral Research Fellowship – <b>by Competition</b> Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec), (60 000\$CAD)
08/2010	Mention d'Honneur – Top Score Thesis Faculté des Sciences, Université du Québec à Montréal
09/2008 - 08/2010	Master Research Fellowship – <b>by Competition</b> Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec), (30 000\$CAD)
05/2008 - 08/2008	Summer Research Grant $LaCIM-UQAM$ , (5 000\$CAD)
05/2007	Math in Moscow Scholarship – <b>by National Competition</b> CMS and NSERC Scholarship (Canada), 3 Prizes/Year, (9 000\$CAD)
05/2007 - 08/2007	Summer Research Grant – by Competition  NSERC, (6250\$CAD)
05/2006 - 08/2006	Summer Research Grant – by Competition  NSERC, (6250\$CAD)
08/2005 - 04/2006	Tableau d'Honneur – Perfect Grade Point Average (4.3/4.3) Département de Mathématiques et Statistique, Université Laval

# SELECTED SCIENTIFIC INVITATIONS

### <u>FPSAC International Conferences</u> (acceptance: ≈5% talk, ≈15% poster)

Tel Aviv Israel (Poster, 2020), Daejeon South Korea (Poster, 2015), Chicago USA (Poster, 2014), Nagoya Japan (2 Talks, 2012)

# Research invitations

Oberwolfach Discrete Geometry (09/2020), Oberwolfach Algorithms in Polyhedral Geometry (Research in Pairs, 04/2019), Institute for Mathematics and its Applications – Minneapolis (Research in Pairs, 04/2018), Oberwolfach Algebraic and Geometric Combinatorics (02/2015), Centre International de Rencontres Mathématiques (05/2010)

### Invited Talks

AMS Sectional Meeting Geometric and Topological Combinatorics (11/2019), Institute for Mathematics and its Applications (08/2017), Encuentro Colombiano de Combinatoria (06/2016)

# Combinatorics & Geometry Seminars

Max Planck Institute Leipzig (03/2020), UCLA (11/2019), University of Southern California (11/2019), University of Washington (11/2019), University of Miami (11/2019), Institut Henri-Poincaré (03/2019), LaBRI Bordeaux (11/2017)

#### Referee

Transactions of the AMS, Annales Henri Lebesgue, Experimental Mathematics, Israel Journal of Mathematics, Journal of Algebra, Algebraic Combinatorics, Discrete & Computational Geometry, New York Journal of Mathematics, Beiträge zur Algebra und Geometrie, Journal of Combinatorial Theory A, European Journal of Combinatorics, Electronic Journal of Combinatorics, Séminaire Lotharingien de Combinatorice, Discrete Mathematics, Australasian Journal of Combinatorics, Publicationes Mathematicae Debrecen

### Organizer

- 2× Chair of organization committee (Sage Days 79, 1st BMS Student Conference)
- 5× Member of international organization committee (ECCO 2020, 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> BMS–BGSMath Joint Junior Meeting, Sage Days 84, Coxeter Groups meet Convex Geometry 2012)
- $\bullet$  2× Member of organization committee of research seminars at the Freie Universität Berlin (Discrete Geometry group seminar, Polyhedral Combinatorics research seminar)

### Thesis Advisorship

■ Doctoral student: 1 on-going

■ Master students: 3 completed

■ Bachelor students: 3 completed, 1 on-going

### Past and present committees

- Examination: 5 bachelor theses, 1 master thesis, 3 PhD Qualifying Exams, 3 PhD Defenses
- Hiring: 2 post-doctoral positions
- Representation: elected student representative  $(3\times)$ , appointed postdoctoral faculty spokesperson  $(2\times)$ , board member (Berlin Mathematical School, Facets of Complexity Graduate School), Early Career Representative for the Berlin Excellence Strategy University Alliance

#### References

Günter M. Ziegler (PhD Advisor) Eran Nevo

Freie Universität Berlin, Germany Hebrew University Jerusalem, Israel

Victor Reiner Francisco Santos

University of Minnesota, USA Universidad de Cantabria, Spain

Matthias Beck (Habil. Vorsitzender) Volkmar Welker

San Francisco State University, USA Philipps-Universität Marburg, Germany

#### Interests

### Languages

French: Native speaker English: Fluent German: Fluent Russian: Pushkin State Institute, Moscow Spanish: Upper Intermediate Italian: Beginner

McGill University (Advanced 2)

Hungarian: Budapest Semesters (Beginner) Hebrew: Beginner

### Cycling

- Constructed three single-speed bikes
- Cyclo-camping: Québec City Îles-de-la-Madeleine (1200km in 7 days)
- Race: Vélothon Berlin 2012 (60km in 1h38min12sec)

### Other

Colonial History of the Americas Ultimate frisbee Sustainable gardening Theater of the Absurd French poetry Fine Woodworking